上一节我们看了ElGamal公钥加密系统
In the last segment, we saw that the
ElGamal public key encryption system is
是选择密文安全的，基于一个有点奇怪的假设。本节
chosen cipher text secure under a somewhat
strange assumption. In this segment, we're
我们要看一些ElGamal的变种，它们有着更好的
gonna look at variants of ElGamal that
have a much better chosen cipher text
选择密文安全的分析。现在，我应该说，在过去的十年里
security analysis. Now, I should say that
over the past decade, there's been a ton
有大量的构建选择密文安全的公钥加密的研究
of research on constructing, public key
encryptions that are chosen cipher text
其实关于如何最好地展示这部分内容，我一度拿不定主意
secure. I actually debated for some time
on how to best present this here. And
最终我决定为大家展示一遍过去十年主要结果的综述
finally, I decided to kind of show you a
survey of the main results from the last
特别是它们应用到ElGamal系统的方面。然后
decades, specifically as they apply to the
ElGamal system. And then, at the end of
在本章的最后，我会给大家介绍很多论文，
大家可以做进一步的阅读
the module, I suggest a number of papers
that you can look at for further reading.
那么一开始让我提醒大家ElGamal加密系统的工作原理
So let me start by reminding you how the
ElGamal encryption system works. I'm sure
我确定到现在大家应该都记得ElGamal如何工作的，
但为了万无一失，我还是提醒一下
by now you all remember how ElGamal works,
but just to be safe, let me remind you
ElGamal的密钥生成中，选取一个Z_N中的随机生成元
that key generation in ElGamal picks a
random generator, a random exponent from ZN
和一个随机指数，然后公钥由生成元和这个元素
计算得到，即g^a
and then the public key is simply the
generator and this element g to the a,
同时，私钥就是离散对数log_g h，即这个值a
whereas the secret key is simply the
discrete log of h base g. This value A.
现在我们加密的方法是，选择一个Z_N中的随机指数b
Now the way we encrypt is we pick a random
exponent B from ZN. We compute the hash of
我们计算(g^b, h^b)的哈希值。我要提醒大家
G to the B and H to the B. And I'm gonna
remind you that H to the B is the Diffie
h^b是Diffie-Hellman密钥。然后我们加密信息
Hellman secret, G to the AB. And then we
actually encrypt a message using a
使用一个对称加密系统，以及密钥k，
k是由这个哈希函数推导来的
symmetric encryption system with the key K
that's derived from the hash function. And
最后，输出密文是g^b和对称加密后的密文
finally, the output cipher text is G to
the B, and the symmetric cipher text. The
我们解密的方法是，就像我们之前看到的
way we decrypt is you know, as we've seen
before basically, by hashing U and the
计算u和Diffie-Hellman密钥的哈希值，解密对称密文
Diffie Hellman secrets, decrypting the
symmetric system, and outputting the
输出明文m。在上一节里，我们说过ElGamal是选择密文安全的
message M. Now in the last segment we said
that ElGamal is chosen ciphertext secure under
基于这个滑稽的交互Diffie-Hellman假设。
我在这里就不再提醒大家
this funny Interactive Diffie-Hellman
assumption. I am not gonna remind you what
这个假设是什么了，但我要说，这个定理自然地
the assumption is here but I'll also say
that this theorem kind of raises two very
提出了两个问题：第一个是，我们能否证明
natural questions. The first question is
can we prove CCA security of
ElGamal的CCA安全性，基于标准的计算Diffie-Hellman假设？
ElGamal just based on the standard
Computational Diffie-Hellman assumption,
即由g^a, g^b，你不能计算出g^ab
namely the G to the A, G to the B, you
can't compute G to the AB. Can we prove
我们能否只根据这点，就能证明选择密文安全性？
事实上有两种方法能做到这点
chosen-ciphertext security just based on
that? And the truth's that there are two
第一个方法是使用
ways to do it. The first option is to use
a group where the computational Diffie
计算Diffie-Hellman假设为困难的群。
但可以证明它与交互式Diffie-Hellman假设等价
Hellman assumption is hard. But is
provably equivalent to the Interactive
实际上不难组建这样的群
Diffie Hellman assumption. And it turns
out it's actually not that hard to
这些群叫做双线性群
construct such groups. These groups are
called bilinear groups. And in such
(双线性群上的二元运算是(0,2)型张量)
在这些群里，ElGamal系统是选择密文安全的
groups, we know that the ElGamal system is
chosen cipher text secure, strictly based
严格地基于计算Diffie-Hellman假设得证，
至少是在随机神谕模型下得证的
under the Computational Diffie Hellman
assumption, at least in the random oracle
我告诉大家这些双线性群是根据非常特殊的
model. I'll tell you that these bi-linear
groups are actually constructed from very
椭圆曲线构建的，它们具有更多的代数结构
special elliptic curves. So there's a bit
more algebraic structure that enables us
(可以参考Weil配对和Tate配对)
可以使得我们证明IDH和CDH的等价性。但一般地
to prove this equivalence of IDH and CDH.
But in general, who knows, maybe you don't
也许你根本就不想用椭圆曲线群，
也许你就想用Z_p^*，出于某些原因
want to use elliptic curve groups, maybe
you want to use ZP star for some reason.
那么这是一个很自然的问题要问。
我们能否修改ElGamal系统
So it's a pretty natural question to ask.
Can we change the ElGamal system such that
使得ElGamal的选择密文安全可以被证明，直接使用CDH即可
chosen ciphertext security of ElGamal now can be proven, directly based on CDH, for any group
对于任意群CDH都是困难的？现在不用假设群上的任何附加结构
where CDH is hard? Now without assuming
any additional structure about the group,
实际上答案是肯定的，有一个优雅的机制
And it turns out the answer is yes. And
there's kind of an elegant construction
叫做孪生ElGamal，那么让我们为大家展示
孪生ElGamal是怎么工作的
called twin ElGamal, so let me show you
how twin ElGamal works. It's a very simple
它是ElGamal的一个简单变种，如下工作：
在密钥生成阶段，我们选择一个
variation of ElGamal that does the
following. Again, in key generation, we
随机生成元，但这次我们选择两个指数a1和a2
choose a random generator. But this time,
we're gonna choose two exponents, A1 and
作为私钥。那么私钥将由这两个指数a1和a2组成
A2 as the secret key. So the secret key is
gonna consist of these two exponents, A1
大家知道公钥当然是由我们的生成元组成
and A2. You know the public key of course
is gonna consist of our generator. And
然后我们公布g^a1和g^a2。记得在常规ElGamal中
then we're gonna release G to the A1 and G
to the A2. So remember that in regular
公钥只是g^a就行了。这里我们有两个指数
ElGamal what the public key is simply g
to the A and that's it. Here we have two
a1和a2，所以我们要公布g^a1和g^a2
exponents A1 and A2 and therefore we, we
release both G to the A1 and G to the A2.
现在我们加密的方法是，大家注意，
这里公钥比常规ElGamal
Now the way we encrypt, you'll notice the
public key here is one element longer than
多出一个元素。我们使用公钥加密的方法
regular ElGamal. The way we encrypt using
this public key is actually very similar
与常规ElGamal很类似。我们选择一个随机数b，
现在我们不去计算
to regular ElGamal. We choose a random B,
and now what we'll hash is actually not
(g^b,h1^b)的哈希，而是(g^b,h1^b,h2^b)的哈希
just G to the B and H1 to the B, but,
in fact, G to the B, H1 to the B, and H2
好，那么我们计算三个元素的哈希，而非两个
to the B. Okay so we basically hashing
three elements instead of two elements and
然后我们使用推出的对称加密密钥来加密信息
then we basically encrypt the message
using the derived symmetric encryption key
通常我们输出g^b和c作为我们最终的密文。那我们如何解密？
and as usual we output g to the b and c as our
final ciphertext. How do we decrypt?
那么现在私钥由两个指数a1和a2组成
Well, so now the secret key consists of
these two exponents, A1 and A2. And the
密文由u和对称密文c组成。那么让我问大家
cipher text consists of U, and the
symmetric cipher text C. So let me ask you
一个问题，看看大家是否能想出来，
如何推出对称加密密钥k？
a puzzle, and see if you can figure out
how to derive the symmetric encryption key
只有私钥和值u。那么这道题很有意思
K, just given the secret key and the value
U. So it's kind of a cute puzzle and I
我希望大家都能解出来。答案是
hope everybody worked out, the solution
which is basically what we can do is we
我们可以取u的a1次方，即g^(ba1)，以及u^a2
can take U to the power of A1, and that is
basically G to the B A1 And U to the A2
即g^(ba2)。这会给我们一模一样的值
which is G to the B A2. And that basically
gives us exactly the same values, as H1 to
也就是h1^b和h2^b。那么这样子，解密者会得到与加密者同样的
the B and H2 to the B. So this way the
decryptor arrives at the same symmetric
对称密钥。然后他使用对称系统的密钥解密了密文
key that the encryptor did. Then he decrypts
the ciphertext using the symmetric system
最终输出明文m。那么大家注意到这是一个非常简单的
and finally outputs the message M. So you
notice this is a very simple modification
对常规ElGamal的修改。我们在公钥里添加一个元素
to regular ElGamal. All we do is we stick
one more element to the public key. When
当我们计算哈希时，我们多计算一个元素，不只有2个
we do the hashing, we hash one more
element, as opposed to just two elements.
我们求三个元素的哈希值。类似地，我们进行解密，没什么变化
We hash three elements. And similarly, we
do doing decryption, and nothing else
密文长度也不变，就完事了
changes. The cipher text is the same
length as before, and that's it, Now the
现在惊人的是，这个简单的改变可以让我们
amazing thing is that this simple
modification allows us to now prove chosen
根据计算Diffie-Hellman假设来证明选择密文安全了
cipher text security directly based on
standard Computational Diffie-Hellman
不过我们依然需要假设，我们有一个
assumption, okay? Still we're going to
need to assume that we have a symmetric
提供了认证加密的对称加密系统
encryption system that provides us
authenticated encryption and that the hash
我们使用的哈希函数是一个理想的哈希函数，即所谓随机神谕
function that we're using is an ideal hash
function in what we call a random oracle
不过有了这个，我们就可以证明选择密文安全
But nevertheless given that, we can
prove chosen cipher text security strictly
严格地根据计算Diffie-Hellman假设了。那么代价是什么？
based on a Computational Diffie-Hellman
assumption. So now what's the cost of this?
当然，如果大家想想，在加密、解密过程中
Of course, if you think about this, during
encryption and decryption, encryption has
加密必须多做一次指数，解密必须多做一次指数
to do one more exponentiation, and the
decryption has to do one more
所以加密者现在要做3次指数，而非2次
exponentiation. So the encryptor now does
three exponentiations instead of two, and
解密者要做2次指数而非1次。现在的问题是
the decryptor does two exponentiations
instead of one. So the question is now,
这是个哲学问题。这种多余的开销值得做吗？
now it's a philosophical question. Is this
extra effort worth it? So you do more work
那么加解密的工作变多了。公钥变长了
during encryption and decryption. And your
public key is a little bit bigger, but
但效果并不重要。在加解密上的工作
that doesn't really matter. The work
during encryption and decryption is more
更为重要些。因此大家获得了选择密文安全
significant. And as a result you get
chosen ciphertext security based on kind
基于某种自然的假设，即计算Diffie-Hellman
of a more natural assumption, namely
Computational Diffie-Hellman as opposed to
而非这些奇怪的交互Diffie-Hellman假设
these odd-looking Interactive
Diffie-Hellman assumption. But is it worth
但这样做值得吗？这些CDH成立，但IDH不成立的群
it? Kind of the question is are there
groups where CDH holds but IDH does not
如果存在这样的群，那么这么做当然是值得的
hold? If there were such groups, then it
would definitely be worth it, because
因为在这些群上，孪生ElGamal将是安全的，
而常规ElGamal将不是CCA安全的
those groups, the twin ElGamal would be
secure, but the regular ElGamal would not
但不幸的是，我们不知道这样的群是否存在
be CCA secure. But unfortunately we don't
know if there is any such group and in
事实上我们目前只知道，有的群上CDH成立
fact as far as we know, it's certainly
possible that any group where CDH holds,
IDH也成立。那么答案是，我们不知道多余的开销
IDH also holds. So the answer is, really,
we don't know whether the extra cost is
是否值得，但是这个结果很可爱，证实了
worth it or not but then nevertheless it's
a cute result that shows that if you want
如果你想直接从CDH获得选择密文安全
to achieve chosen ciphertext
security directly from CDH, you could do
你是可以做到的，无需对ElGamal系统做太多修改。下个问题是
it without too many changes to the ElGamal
system. The next question is whether we
我们能否回避这个哈希函数是理想的假设？
can get rid of this assumption that the
hash function is an ideal hash function
即假设哈希函数是随机神谕。这是一个很大的研究方向
mainly that it's a random oracle. And this
is actually a huge topic. There's a lot of
这个方向里有很多研究工作，研究
如何构建公钥加密系统
work in this area on how to build
efficient public key encryption systems
以达到不借助随机神谕的选择密文安全
that are chosen ciphertext secure without
random oracles. This is a very active area
这一个很活跃的研究领域，如我所说，在过去的十年
甚至更长的时间里
of research as I said in the past decade
and even longer. And I'll mention that as
应用到ElGamal的，主要有两类机制
it applies to ElGamal, they are basically,
again two families of constructions. The
第一个机制使用了特殊的群
first construction's a construction that
uses these special groups called these
叫做双线性群，我刚刚提过。实际上
bilinear groups that I just mentioned
before. It turns out the extra structure
这些双线性群的多余结构允许我们构建很有效的
of these bilinear groups allows us to
build very efficient chosen ciphertext
选择密文安全的系统，无需依靠随机神谕，如我所说
secure systems without referring to random
oracles and as I said at the end of the
在本章最后。我将指出很多论文进行进一步解释
module, I point to a number of papers that
explain how to do that. This is quite an
这是一个很有趣的机制。但它会花掉我几个小时
interesting construction. But it will take
me several hours to kind of explain how it
去解释它是怎么工作的。其他机制则是使用了特定群
works. The other alternative is actually
to use groups where a stronger assumption
这些群上满足更强的假设，叫做判定Diffie-Hellman假设
called the Decision Diffie-Hellman assumption
holds. Again, I am not gonna define this
我这里也不给出其定义了。我只是告诉大家这个假设
assumption here. I'll just tell you that
this assumption actually holds in
在Z_p^*中成立，特别地，如果我们看Z_p^*的质数阶子群
subgroups of ZP star, in particular if we
look at the prime order of a subgroup of
判定Diffie-Hellman假设似乎在这些群上成立
ZP star. The Decision Diffie-Hellman
assumption seems to hold in those groups
那么在这些群上我们就可以构建一种ElGamal的变种
and then in those groups we can actually
build a variant of ElGamal, called the
叫做Cramer-Shoup系统，它是选择密文安全的
Cramer Shoup system that is chosen
ciphertext secure and the Decision
在判定Diffie-Hellman假设下，且无需随机神谕。
这是一个漂亮的结果
Diffie-Hellman assumption without random
oracles. Again, this is a beautiful,
但是它也需要几个小时去解释，我这里就不做了
beautiful result but again it would take a
couple of hours to explain and so I'm not
这很可能是我留作高级课题
gonna do that here. This is probably one
of these things that I gonna leave to
或高级课程的内容之一，这样我们以后再说
either the advanced topics or to do an
advanced course so that we'll do it at a
我在章末指出一篇论文
later time. But again I points to a paper
at the end of the module just in case you
如果大家想了解更多。这里的论文列表提供了更多的阅读材料
want to read more about this. So here is a
list of papers that provides more reading
那么如果大家想了解更多的Diffie-Hellman假设
material. So if you wanna read about
Diffie Hellman assumptions, I guess I
我想我很早写过一篇论文是关于这个的，
讨论了大量的Diffie-Hellman的相关假设
wrote a paper about this a long time ago,
that talks about various assumptions
特别地，研究了判定Diffie-Hellman假设
related to, to Diffie Hellman. And in
particular, studies the Decision Diffie
如果大家想学习如何构建选择密文安全的系统
Hellman assumption. And if you wanna learn
about how to build chosen ciphertext
根据判定Diffie-Hellman和类似假设
secure system from Decision Diffie-Hellman
and assumptions like it. There's a very
Kramer和Shoup在2002年有一篇很好的文章是讨论这个的
cute paper by Kramer and Shoup back
from 2002 that shows how to do it. This is
这也是一篇非常推荐的论文。如果大家想学习
again a very highly recommended paper. If
you want to learn how to build chosen
如何从双线性群构建选择密文安全性，那么这篇论文
ciphertext security from these
bilinear groups, then the paper to read is
在这里引用的这篇，使用了一个一般的机制叫做
the one, cited here, which actually uses a
general mechanism called Identity Based
基于身份的加密，令人惊讶的是它实际上给了我们
Encryption which very surprisingly it
turns out to actually gives us chosen
选择密文安全，几乎没有开销。那么一旦我们构建了
ciphertext security almost for free.
So, once we build identity-based
基于身份的加密，立即就有选择密文安全
encryption chosen ciphertext security falls
immediately. And that's covered in this
这些是在我讲的这篇论文里讨论的。孪生Diffie-Hellman机制
paper that I, that I describe here. The
Twin Diffie-Hellman construction and its
及其证明在这篇论文里描述，我在这里引用的
proof is described in this paper that I
reference here And finally, if you kind of
最后如果大家想看一篇很近的论文，给出了很一般的框架
want to see a very recent paper. That
gives a very general framework for
用来构建选择密文安全的系统，使用所谓的易解哈希证明
building, chosen ciphertext secure systems, using
what's called extractable hash proofs that
这是Hoeteck Wee的一篇好文章，就是最近发表的
is again a nice paper by Hoeteck Wee, that
was just recently published. I definitely
我当然推荐都读一读，它们都有着非常优美的想法
recommend reading it all, all have
very, very elegant ideas in them. I wish I
我希望我可以在密码学基础课程里把它们都讲一讲
could cover all of them in the basic
course but I'm gonna have to leave some of
但我想把它们中的一部分留到更高阶的课程里，
也许就是本课程的最后部分
these to the more advanced course or
perhaps the more advanced topics at the
好，我就讲到这里，下节我将把
end of this course. Okay, so I'll stop
here and in the next segment I'm gonna tie
ElGamal和RSA加密联系在一起，这样大家会看到
ElGamal and RSA encryption
together so that you see how the two kind
两者遵循着更一般的原理
of follow from a more general principle.